Guide to the Willem J. Kolff audio-visual collection 1949-1995
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
- Artificial heart, 1958-1985
  - Artificial heart inside the chest, 1958-61; 16mm film Silent, black and white and color (Reel 59)
    1 Valve in testing machine. Color regular film, then high speed film (1400 fps).
    2 Norton heart in hand and in dog. Dog on image amplifier.
    3 Pendulum heart in mock circulation. Blood is poured into the mock circulation to show its course.
    4 Bellofram heart in mock circulation showing the two different hearts, right and left; the level in the venous reservoir stays constant with considerable flow.
    5 Thrombosis on atrioventricular patches. The first is Teflon and the second is silastic, with thrombi growing along the legs and one thrombus under the patch.
    6 NASA control tower with Wolfgang Seidel, Spyridon Moulopoulos, Sanborn recording equipment to left. The excursion of the pistons is shown on the scope.
    7 Forty-eight potentiometers to define the shape of the electrical function of the NASA equipment. Recording of electrical function, resulting ventricular pressure, and blood flow as measured with a thermistor in the mock circulation.
    Result of gentle ventricular pressure on the top of the aorta showing gentle flow and abrupt ventricular pressure showing abrupt flow, followed by another set of recordings with changes of electrical function and simultaneous changes in ventricular pressure due to a steep curve. The Akutsu heart pulsed gently, then pulsed abruptly so that it jumps on the table, then gently.
    8 Norton air driven heart. Reciprocating air pump pumping the two ventricles with anti-suction bellows where the inlet and outlet to one ventricle are occluded by hand. The anti-suction bellows, or ballon, collapses during diastole.
    9 Dog on the operating table five hours after insertion of a Bellofram heart inside the chest. Next, the dog on a platform eight hours after insertion. Next, the same dog ten hours after insertion.
  - Angiocardiograms, 1962; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 60)
    Labeled "Dog 305 G." Five minutes.
  - Old total heart procedure, 1962; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 61)
    This presents the preparation of a calf for surgery and the removal of the calf's heart and its replacement with an artificial heart. Shows calf, later, in suspension, along with the monitoring equipment. Eight minutes.
  - Calf experiments 1 and 2, 1963 October-November; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 62)
    This film shows Dr. Kolff with a calf that is recovering from installation of an artificial heart; the interior of the laboratory and monitoring equipment; the calf drinking water; the calf in suspension hammock with the medical team. 7 minutes.
  - Artificial heart In chest, 1959-1964; 16mm film Silent, black and white and color (Reel 63)
    1 Tricuspid valve in mock circulation. Ordinary movie with high-speed factors.
    2 Electromotor driven, pendulum type heart in mock circulation.
    3 Dog on table with chest closed and solenoid driven heart inside. Its own heart shows mitral valve inside. Cineangiocardiograms of same (Sones, 1959).
    4 Seidel and Moulopoulos on NASA time scope.
    5 Forty-eight potentiometers. Also, quiet pumping and turbulent pumping.
    6 Dog on table waking up from anesthesia, 1961.
    7 Tricuspid mitral valves made of Teflon patches in the ventricles.
    Atrioventricular window patch.
    8 Manufacturing of Silastic heart. Cerrotru mold with the ball valves inside are being layered. Finished product (right ventricle).
    9 Calf being given water and in suspension.
    10 Heart with anti-suction bellows added. 11 minutes.
  - Pendulum in mock circulation, 1965; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 64)
    1 Pendulum heart in mock circulation. Filling with blood to show sequence of flow.
    2 Layering of Silastic hearts. First, cerrotru molds, then balls in place. Next, layering with Silasticirca Right and left sides.
    3 NASA Tower. Scope movement of the ventricles.
    4 Black calf on table given water from a syringe.
    5 Brown calf suspended with adhesive tape
    6 Black calf with a heart driven by a fluid amplifier trying to run. Suspended with bone pins.
  - Fluid amplifier heart, 1965; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 65)
    Shows artificial heart pumping in a chest. One minute.
  - Artificial heart inside the chest 1, 1964-65; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 66)
    Sequence: Plaster ventricular cavity molds; right atrial and ventricular molds by electroplating; rotational cavity molding PUC of hollow molds; plastic parts (atrium, ventricle, aorta); valve molds; completed heart (first model); sewing rings for atrium attachment; mock circulation; dead dog--heart placement; first in a live dog, December 12, 1957; wooden model of solenoid heart; actual solenoid heart; mock circulation; dog with solenoid heart; cineangiocardiogram of solenoid heart; back view of solenoid pump; solenoid pump in mock circulation; polyurethane working techniques; polyurethane valves; corrugated vessels; dip molding polyurethane ventricles; removing polyurethane parts from model; plastic parts for solenoid pump; cineangiocardiogram of valve in a dog; and view of solenoid. 25 minutes.
  - Artificial heart inside the chest 2, 1965; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 67)
    Sequence: Pendulum heart in mock circulation; close-up of pendulum; air driven hearts; NASA control equipment; wave form of driving air pressure; demonstration of recoil due to abrupt driving air pressure; dog with heart in chest. Wires being repaired; NASA control equipment and recorders, Seidel and Molopoulous; dog coming out of anesthesia with an artificial heart; Norton reciprocating air pump; Norton hearts, right and left; Norton drive (newer model); vacuum control system, anti-suction bellows; devcon master molds for Silastic hearts; molding technique for RTV Silastic; removal of molds; inside of molds; making of metal disposable casts; assembly of casts; layering of silastic on metal molds; completed Silastic heart with coils; Holter company; Holter injection molds; finishing disposable metal molds; removal of metal mold by melting; assembly of artificial heart; testing air driven artificial hearts in mock circulation; recording equipment; calf with artificial heart; tracing; and calf drinking water. 32 minutes.
  - Artificial heart inside the chest, 1965; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 68)
    Sequence: Testing of valves; testing machine; tricuspid valve on high speed pictures; bad valve in tester; natural valve of a dog in testing machine; polyurethane valves; placement of a tricuspid valve in a dog (natural heart); cineangiocardiogram of mitral in a dog; rubber valves in testing machine; valve in a natural heart showing clot; plastic patches for clot investigation; clots in plastic valve in a dog's heart; woven Teflon valves, clotted. 20 minutes.
  - Artificial heart inside the chest, 1965; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 69)
    A compilation recording of items 66 and 67. 60 minutes.
  - Fluid amplifier heart, 1966; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 70)
    Shows the activities of a calf in suspension.
  - Left heart bypass, 1966; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 71)
    This film shows segments of bypass surgery on a sheep, using an external heart machine. 7 minutes.
  - Animal suspension and artificial heart re-circulation, 1960-1966; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 72)
    Demonstrates the older method of suspending an animal while it is recovering from installation of an artificial heart. This also shows a type of artificial heart in a re-circulation position outside of the animal. 3 minutes
  - Artificial heart implant test film, 1966 August 18; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 73)
    Footage of the implantation of an artificial heart; footage of a calf connected to monitoring equipment and in suspension. Two minutes.
  - Artificial heart control system, 1966; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 74)
    This film discusses the functioning of the artificial heart; the control system developed by NASA; the components of that system; and how it works. Written by Michael J. Crosby and Kirby W. Hiller; produced by NASA (film serial C247). 17 minutes.
  - Artificial heart, 1969; 8mm film Silent, color (Reel 75)
    This is a copy of an 8mm film made by Albert Kolff showing Dr. Kolff and building 512 at the University of Utah and at a meeting; the manufacture of an artificial heart; mock circulation; surgery and monitoring equipment.
  - Artificial heart insertion, 1970; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 76)
    Shows medical personnel in conference, operating room and surgery footage of artificial heart insertion in a calf.
  - Total heart replacement in aheep, 1970 March; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 77)
    The sheep who is operated on in this film is identified as TR 4 -70. This film shows the intibation and preparation of the sheep followed by the opening of the chest, the bypassing of the heart, pulsatile return, dissection of the heart, insertion of the artery connector also known as the flow probe, insertion of the aortic connector, viewing of the right atrium, and the connection of the right then left ventricles. It then shows the heart pumping, the closing of the chest and the sheep recovering from the anesthesia.
  - Calves with artificial hearts, 1971 April 20 (Reel 78)
    Six scenes of lab personnel feeding calf with artificial heart. Label on cage in film is TH 71 C11 F4. Canister label identifies "Pam, Kwan-G." Five minutes.
  - Artificial Heart, 1971 April; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 79)
    One week survival of calf with an artificial heart. Includes section on hypothermia and a list of team members. Credited to University of Utah College of Medicine, Department of Surgery and the Institute of Biomedical Engineering. 10 minutes.
  - Operation footage, 1971 March 02 (Reel 80)
    The canister is labeled "Hypothermia; Drs. Peters, Kawai, Zwart. The footage shows preparation for surgery, chest surgery on a calf and a process of immersing the calf in ice before surgery and water after surgery. Afterwards, the calf is seen recovering at 99 and 100 hours after the operation and there are views of the monitoring equipment.
  - Calf film, undated; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 81)
    Three films:
    A: H. Zwart and J. Kawai with calf attempting to insert endotracheal tube. Three minutes.
    B: Shows University of Utah Building 512 (Division of Artificial Organs) and the Park Building. As well as, H. Zwart and J. Kawai with a calf in the recovery cage. Views of monitoring equipment. Three minutes.
    C: The making a K-G diaphragm; Mixing of unidentified chemicals; and finally,
    H. Zwart and J. Kawai giving water to a calf in the recovery cage.
  - Unlimited Future for the Artificial Heart, 1971 November 18; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 82)
    This address, "Unlimited Future for the Artificial Heart, was presented by Dr. Kolf at a symposium on artificial organs at the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California. Kolff is introduced by Dave Yen. This recording was provided for Dr. Kolff by Dr. N. W. Tschoegl through the California Institute of Technology's Office of Public Relations.
  - Calf with artificial heart, 1972 February; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 83)
    Canister label identifies TH72 C6 B6 DV4, "300 hr. calf." The film itself is labeled TH72 C10 B8 DC 5 AEC 2. The footage is of lab attendants working with calf, feeding it, getting it to stand. There are views of the monitoring equipment in the lab. Five minutes.
  - Calf: 300 hours, March 1972; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 84)
    Records a calf in a laboratory cage with a doctor and monitoring equipment. A sign in the scene denotes hours with the artificial heart as 289. The Calf eats and drinks. Five minutes.
  - Calf with artificial heart, 1972 March 07; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 85)
    Canister identifies calf as TH 72 C10 B8 DC5 AEC2.
  - Sheep in surgery, 1976 February; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 86)
    This film shows the prepartion of a sheep for surgery, the insertion of a tracheal tube; chest surgery; monitoring equipment; preparing sheep for recovery; and the view of Salt Lake City from the Avenues. Made by Academy Production Co., Ltd; Suginami-Ku, Tokyo. Eight minutes.
  - Implantation G7V7-4, 1984 February 23; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 87)
    Shows surgery from an overhead viewpoint, in which a calf's (?) heart is removed and replaced with an artificial heart. 240 minutes.
  - Heart and portable driver, 1985 January 16; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 88)
    This videocassette shows the portable heart drive system, developed by Peter Heimes, and its operation in conjunction with the Jarvik 7 heart. Also, footage of the operating room during the installation of Barney Clark's artificial heart. Made by Symbion, Incirca 17 minutes.
- Artificial Organs, 1983-1985
  The section on other artificial organs includes material concerning work on the artificial arm and artificial ear at the University of Utah.
  - Artificial organs, 1983; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 89)
    1 "The Challenge of Artificial Organs" was made by Skyline Productions. Ontario, Canada, and includes views of the Dumke building; Dr. Kolff Speaking on his role and aims at the University of Utah; the Jarvik 7 heart and ventricular assist devices; the dialysis center and progress in dialysis; "Dialysis In
    Wonderland" with John Warner and Lauraine Stephen; comments by Dr. Robert Jarvik on his artificial heart and drive mechanism; animal subjects; and Dr. Don Eddington and the artificial ear.
    2 "The Utah Artificial Arm" shows Dr. Stephen L. Jacobsen explaining the operation of the artificial arm. The credits list the names of the engineering team led by Dr. Jacobsen. 47 minutes.
  - Artificial organs today, 1985; Audiocassette (Cassette 90)
    A recording of a speech made by Dr. Kolff at Accounting and Finance Conference. Topics include reminiscences of the Second World War, the invention of the artificial kidney and recovery rates; slide presentation on artificial kidney development; the wearable artificial kindney; patient selection; questions from audience concerning the cost of artificial organs; a discussion of the intraortic balloon pump; the Jarvik heart; Barney Clark and details of his case; and the artificial ear and eye. Kolff speaks out against increased United States militarization. Continued on side B. 45 minutes.
    A continuation of side A. Two minutes.
  - Interview with Scott Shepherd, 1985 January 08; U-matic videocassette Silent (Cassette 91)
    Shepherd uses an "Ineraid" artificial ear. In this interview, he gives advice for others who could use the artificial ear and describes the level of "understanding" he has attained, as well as the quality of his life. Includes diagrams on how the "Ineraid" system works. Made by Symbion, Incirca Five minutes.
- Miscellaneous items, 1949-1995
  - Artificial kidney in Korean War, 1953; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 92)
    This film documents use of an artificial kidney in military field hospitals during the Korean War. Shown are the 11th Evacuation Hospital, transfer of a patient from helicopter to hospital, his treatment by medical personnel, and the preparation and use of an artificial kidney. 30 minutes.
  - Heart research news, 1955; 16mm film Sound, black and white (Reel 93)
    Persented by the National Heart Institute. Narrated by Charles Rodgers and
    produced by the Heart Information Center.
    1 "Alpha-Methyl DOPA proves effective for hypertension."
    2 "Countershocks saves hearts with abnormal rhythms."
    3 "Diet modification shown practical in pilot study."
    4 "Profile of aging emerging from unique National Heart Institute study."
    5 "Conduction system locator helps lesser dangers of open-heart surgery."
    6 "Computer monitoring of fetal ECG may save lives."
    7 "Microscopy techniques help surgeons repair small blood vessels."
    8 "New heart pump shows worth against heart attack."
    9 "Artificial heart passes first experimental trials." 16 minutes.
  - Internal Medicine; Vol. XI, No. 17, 1964 Seotenver 07; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 94)
    Five papers on a variety of subjects.
    A panel discussion held in Portland, Oregon, which discusses the issues of patient selection and funding for the artificial kidney. Participants are Belding H. Scribner, Professor of Medicine, University of Washington School of Medicine (Moderator); Dr. Kolff; John S. Murray, Clinical Director, Seattle Artificial Kidney Center, The Swedish Hospital, Seattle; and Rev. Robert H. Springer, Professor of Ethics, Loyola Seminary, Shrub Oak, New York. A "Table of Contents" which accompanied this tape is available. 35 minutes.
  - Interview with Dr. Kolff, 1963 August; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 95)
    Recorded from the radio program "Carol's Corner" on WKET, Dayton, OH. The host is Carol Klein. Dr. Kolff speaks about the development, ethics and operation of the artificial kidney.
  - Farm and kidney transplantation picnic, 1964 August 17; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 96)
    Sequence: Allan Pert on tractor to right; people on tractor; tractor & trailer on the way; tractor approaching pond and the dock; people on dock; Ferrara, his wife and >Dr. Nakamoto; Juris Gailitis and boat; Mrs. Nagle putting Allan in boat and calling him in; Nakamoto and Roberts; picnic served from trailer; Mrs. Nagle, son and husband; Dr. Kolff, Allan Pert and Wayne Hasenyager eating; Juris Gailitis and Phillip Routzon eating hotdogs; Mrs. and Mrs. Paul Kuhn; Aslean Cooper and Royce Ann Cooper; and Dr. Kolff. Some of the people in this film are the same transplant patients seen in item 107. Ten minutes.
  - Who shall live?, 1965; 16mm film Sound, black and white (Reel 97)
    A National Broadcasting Company (NBC) News production, narrated by Edwin Newman. This documentary discusses the issues surrounding the use of the artificial kidney. The locale for most of the film is the Seattle Artificial Kidney Center. The film discusses the steps in screening patients for dialysis, the history of the development of the artificial kidney (including an interview with Dr. Kolff), the problems of financing treatment, and the possibilities provided by home dialysis. 20 minutes.
  - The 21st century, 1967; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 98)
    This documentary is concerned with the future of artificial organs and includes comments by Dr. Kolff on kidney donation. Includes footage of kidney transplantation at the Cleveland Clinic, discussion of patient selection, installation of an artificial heart in a calf, and the electrical stimulation of muscles in pursuit of artificial limb technology. Reported by Walter Cronkite. 27 minutes.
  - Everybody's problem, 1968; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 99)
    A documentary on the issues of kidney disease, including Dr. Louis G. Welt on kidney disease prevention and use of the artificial kidney; Dr. John P. Merrill on Kidney transplantation; stories of actual kidney transplantations and the importance of dialysis in treatment of kidney disease. Produced by Educational Media, Incirca and the National Kidney Foundation. 18 minutes.
  - Dialysis picnic at the Hogle's, 1969 September 16; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 100)
    Scenes filmed at a picnic in Utah with musicians, horseback riding and close-ups of participants, including Kolff. Four minutes.
  - Dr. Kolff was here, 1979-1983; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 101)
    Made by AVRO and narrated by Dr. Kolff, this documentary shows Dr. Kolff returning to Kampen, Netherlands, the city where he developed the artificial kidney; discusses the Jarvik heart, artificial arm, eye and ear; and discusses modern dialysis. Kolff relates stories about his experiences in the Second World War; gives his reasons for immigrating to the United States; discusses the wearable artificial kidney; gives his thoughts on transplantation; and discusses his relationship with his wife. 48 minutes.
  - Markant, 1989 November 15; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 102)
    Dr. Kolff narrates. This film discusses dialysis, has views of the Dumke building, and gives biographical information on Dr. Kolff, Kampen, Kolff's war experiences, the Cleveland Clinic, and the University of Utah. It has interviews with nurses who worked with Dr. Kolff in Kampen; and discusses the "Dialysis in Wonderland" program, the artificial heart, and Barney Clark. 50 minutes.
  - Leif Stenberg going to restaurant in Stockholm, 1985; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 103)
    A recording of a trip to a restaurant by a patient using the Heimer drive system.
    Made by Peter Heimer. 17 minutes.
  - On the shoulders of giants, 1985; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 104)
    A recording of ceremonies in which individuals, including Dr. Kolff, who are considered "pioneers" in cardiovascular research, are awarded by the John P. Murphy Foundation in Cleveland, OH.
  - Kolff films, 1949-1972; U-matic videocassette Silent (Cassette 105)
    A compilation of these films (listed above):
    1 Item 1.
    2 Item 75.
    3 Item 59, oxygenator preparation, dog--shows heart removed.
    4 Valve studies and item 39.
    5 Item 64, part 1.
    6 Thrombosis studies.
    7 Item 59, part 6.
    8 Item 63, part 8.
    9 Item 39.
    10 Item 16.
    11 Item 85.
    12 Item 84.
    13 Kolff with dialysis machines (circa1978)and patient.
  - Heart valve studies negatives, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 106)
  - Artificial heart from the Cleveland Clinic, undated; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 107)
    Shows an artificial heart in operation on pump as well as an artificial ventricle, a real ventricle, and a Teflon ventricle with the valves opening and closing. This film also shows Atrioventricular window patches 8-21 days. These include two silastic, one polyurethane smooth, two knitted Teflon, two collagen, and one polyurethane sponge. In closing, they show a monocusp valve.
  - Thermo vacuum forming, 1981-1983; 8mm film (Reel 108)
    Produced by Nannie K.M. De Leeuw
    Different techniques used in thermo vacuum forming in 1981 and in 1982.
  - Dr. V. Mirkovitch, research 6, Cleveland Clinic, undated; 16mm film (Reel 109)
    Seidel's valve until Ciludae? Trend?
    Unedited remains of high speed (something unreadable) of valve in mock circulation. Last part is watchable.
  - Pendulum in mock circulation, undated; 16mm film (Reel 110)
  - National Inventors Hall of Fame induction ceremony, 1992 April 25; VHS videocassette (Cassette 111)
    Includes a letter to Dr. Kolff from Raymond V. Damadian, September 15, 1992.
    Ceremony held at the E. J. Thomas Performing Arts Hall in Akron, Ohio.
  - KUED production: Civic dialogue, 1984 March 02; Audiocassette (Cassette 112)
    Topics: Dr. Kolff, Dr. Brophy, and Dr. Wilson. Interviewer: Clifton Jolley
  - KRCL Production: Life is a creative process, 10 May 1984; Audiocassette (Cassette 113)
    Interview of Dr. Kolff by Desiree Mays.
  - Memoirs and anecdotes by Willem J. Kolff, 1993 September; Microcassette (Cassette 114)
  - Photographic materials transferred to the Willem J. Kolff photograph collection (P0343) (Image 115-116)
  - Patterns of thought for writers conference, 1953; Phonograph record (Disc 117)
    Mrs. M.F.K fisher is the special guest in this series of "Patterns of thought for writers conference". She discusses food and gastronomy as well as the three great hungers: warmth love and food.
  - An envelope containing 5 phono discs., 1967; Phonograph record (Disc 118)
  - An envelope containing a phono disc., 1960; Phonograph record (Disc 119)
    J. Louis Reynolds of the Marquadt Corporation.
  - 13 Folders of Magnetic Dictaphone Cards for the FDA Application., 1981; dictaphone card (Card 120)